<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Confession and execution of the five prisoners that suffered at Tyburn on Wednesday the 19th of Decemb. 1677 viz, Margaret Riggs, alias Grover, William Longman [double brace] John Ruddocke, Henry Payne, and Elizabeth Hewet : with an account of their penitent behaviour after their condemnation, and substance of their last speeches at the place of execution / published for a warning-piece to all others to avoid the lewd courses which brought them to their ignominious end.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80316</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5747A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205229</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875589</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152250</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80316)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152250)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2287:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Confession and execution of the five prisoners that suffered at Tyburn on Wednesday the 19th of Decemb. 1677 viz, Margaret Riggs, alias Grover, William Longman [double brace] John Ruddocke, Henry Payne, and Elizabeth Hewet : with an account of their penitent behaviour after their condemnation, and substance of their last speeches at the place of execution / published for a warning-piece to all others to avoid the lewd courses which brought them to their ignominious end.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D.M.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"With Allowance"</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Executions and executioners --  England.</term>
               <term>Thieves --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152250:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONFESSION AND EXECUTION Of the Five Priſoners that ſuffered at TYBURN On <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 19th of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1677. VIZ.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret Riggs,</hi> alias <hi>Grover,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Longman,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Ruddocke,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry Payne,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Elizabeth Hewet.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>WITH An Account of their penitent Behaviour after their Condemnation, and ſubſtance of their laſt Speeches at the place of Execution.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for a Warning-piece to all others to avoid the lewd Courſes which brought them to this Ignominious End.</p>
            <p>With Allowance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>D. M.</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152250:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152250:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The laſt Speeches, Confeſsion, and Execution of the Priſoners, <hi>December</hi> 19. 1677.</head>
            <p>DEath in its own nature is very af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting to Man, the King of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, much more when he comes attended with ſhameful and ignominious Circumſtances; when Perſons conſider that they have haſtened his approach by the <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi> of their lives, and are juſtly cut off for their Crimes. Oh! how ſad is it, when poor Souls are themſelves the occaſion of their being thruſt out of this world by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely Violence, and yet are not at all fitted or prepared for the next. If they look down to Earth, there is nothing but Juſtice and Vengeance ready to purſue them; and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152250:3"/> if they look up to Heaven, they cannot but conclude that too pure a place for ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Creatures to enter into, whom the Earth it ſelf would no longer entertain. Yet ſo lamentably do the Deluſions of Satan, and Witchcrafts of Sin blinde the eyes of theſe Malefactors, that they rarely reflect on theſe things till it be too late; nor will be warned by the frequent Examples of their wretched Fellow-Criminals, to leave off their wicked Courſes, till they are precipitated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame Gulf of Miſery.</p>
            <p>Of this, the Five Perſons that this day ſuffered were deplorable inſtances. After their Condemnation many charitable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines went to viſit them, beſides the moſt diligent and careful endeavours of Mr. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, who, well knowing the weight of his Office, takes care on all occaſions to diſcharge a good Conſcience therein, by u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all means to make them ſenſible of their ſad Condition, and prepare them for their terrible Change.</p>
            <p>The poor Souls appeared as ignorant and unacquainted with the Principles of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152250:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Religion, except only ſome bare empty notional words, as Heathens. True it is, they profeſt themſelves Chriſtians, and that they hop'd to be ſaved by the Mercies of God; but the odious nature of Sin, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a Saviour, the terms of a New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the nature of Repentance, Faith, and other Evangelical Graces, they were wholly ſtrangers to: But by the pains of theſe Miniſters, God was pleaſed to give them a taſte of theſe precious and moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Truths, though 'tis feared, by their careleſs inſenſible Carriage, ſome of them ſtill were more ſolicitous to get a Reprieve than to get Grace, and minded more to ſave their Lives for a few moments, than their Souls to eternity. So hard it is when Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have gone on all their lives, hardening their hearts in wickedneſs, to be mollified on a ſudden, though ſummon'd to Repentance by a preſent and unavoidable Death.</p>
            <p>One of theſe perſons was heretofore Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and now juſtly brought to ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Another about two years ſince was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed and received Sentence of Death, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152250:4"/> obtaining a Reprieve, after long lying in Newgate, obtain'd his Liberty by the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pardon; but was now brought in for ſtealing a parcel of Swords.</p>
            <p>Another was by trade a Sawyer, and had lived neer <hi>Iſlington:</hi> he had formerly been burnt in the hand, and ſeveral times in Goal; and having lately follow'd the Foot-Pad, was Condemn'd for a Robbery on the Highway.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Riggs</hi> was notoriouſly infamous; ſeveral of her Children had been executed, and ſhe a year or two ago tranſported for ſtealing Silks; but returning before her time, was now again Convicted of ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and call'd to her former Judgement. She caus'd her Coffin to be made &amp; brought into the Priſon to her; and we wiſh that ſhe had provided for her Soul as well as for her Carcaſs.</p>
            <p>The other woman was Convicted about a year and a half ſince, and upon the General Pardon gave Bail to tranſport her ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſuch a time; but never did it, but fell to her old wicked Courſes, in which being now taken, ſhe was Condemned.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152250:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>There was another woman received Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to be Burnt; but ſhe alleadging her ſelf to be quick with Childe, which a Jury of Matrons likewiſe affirmed, that the Innocent Babe might not periſh with the Guilty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Execution for the preſent is ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did.</p>
            <p>The day before their Execution four Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters were to viſit them, and beſtowed much pious pains both in <hi>Exhortation</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> with them, preſſing them to Repent, and Confeſs their Sins, and give Glory to God. To whom one of them was ſo hardy ('tis ſaid) as to declare, That ſhe never in her life, that ſhe could remember, ever felt any Convictions or Checks of Conſcience for her wickedneſs, but now deſired a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſpace, promiſing amendment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But they deſired her not to flatter her ſelf with any ſuch hopes, but rather inſtantly to ſet upon the Work with all her might, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe few minutes ſhe had allowed her, rather than vainly to expect longer time, and miſ-ſpend the preſent.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152250:5"/>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Riggs</hi> Confeſt ſhe had been a notorious ſinner all her days, and that ſhe had been an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of bringing many poor wretches to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely Ends, for which ſhe expreſt much ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; but ſaid, for her own part ſhe did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs ſhe deſerved to die, and had long look'd for it, and deſired the Miniſters to pray for her.</p>
            <p>In the Cart they behaved themſelves very pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitently, weeping and wringing their hands, as likewiſe at the place of Execution; but ſaid little, ſave onely, Deſiring all people to take Example by them, and to remember this, That if they themſelves had took warning when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their Acquaintance, under the ſame Circumſtances, with their dying breath heartily adviſed them to it, they might have prevented this ſhameful untimely Death which now they were to ſuffer. And ſo after Prayers and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Offices uſual on ſuch occaſions, ſurrendred their Souls to the Mercies of God, and their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to Execution.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
